Guide to the Mary Margaret Wade papers, 1966-2007
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mary Margaret Wade papers 1966-2007
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Wade, Mary Margaret
9.4 linear feet Extent: 6555 Items
Artist, writer, and arts educator. Collection contains personal correspondence, photographs, writings and drawings, subject files, ephemera, and clippings. The photographs document Wade's personal life, her art exhibits, and trips to Cuba, Alaska, and Costa Rica. The drawings and writings primarily consist of published versions and drafts of cartoons, as well as some manuscripts of writings and drawings for texts, including the artwork for Have You Ever Seen an Ugly Bride?, an unpublished book by Wade and Elizabeth Lide. The subject files include a file for the Resource Center for Women and Ministry in the South, an abortion rights petition signed by Norma McCorvey, and typescripts documenting the Kilbuck family, who were ancestors of Wade's that were missionaries in Alaska. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
RL.01334
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research, with the exception of a small number of items noted as restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Mary Margaret Wade papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2007.
Biographical Note
A native of Winston-Salem, North Carolina, Mary Margaret Wade received a journalism degree from the University of Georgia and a Master of Education degree from Howard University. She taught art at the independent elementary school, the Atlanta School, and worked with artists' book press Nexus Press. Wade moved to Durham, North Carolina in 1996 and was program director for Arts for Life-Duke, a program for children suffering life-threatening illnesses at Duke University Hospital. Several of her political cartoons and drawings appeared in Southline and were published by Gordon Lish in the early 1990s. Her work was also featured in a solo show at the TULA Foundation Gallery in Atlanta, 1992. Wade served on the board of the Cape Lookout Environmental Camp and the Resource Center for Women and Ministry in the South, and was the Board President of Solterra.
Collection Overview
Collection contains personal correspondence, photographs, writings and drawings, subject files, ephemera, and clippings. The photographs document Wade's personal life, her art exhibits, and trips to Cuba, Alaska, and Costa Rica. The drawings and writings primarily consist of published versions and drafts of cartoons, as well as some manuscripts of writings and drawings for texts, including the artwork for Have You Ever Seen an Ugly Bride?, an unpublished book by Wade and Elizabeth Lide. The subject files include a file for the Resource Center for Women and Ministry in the South, an abortion rights petition signed by Norma McCorvey, and typescripts documenting the Kilbuck family, who were ancestors of Wade's and Moravian missionaries in Alaska in the late 1800s and early 1900s. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Subject Headings
Wade, Mary Margaret; Lide, Elizabeth; Kilbuck, John, 1861-1922; Kilbuck, Edith, 1865-1933; McCorvey, Norma, 1947-; Resource Center for Women and Ministry in the South, Inc.; Cartoonists -- United States; Political cartoons -- United States; Editorial cartoons -- United States; Political cartoons; Photographs; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1966-2007, 2 Boxes
  - Caudle Family, 1986-1998 (Box 1)
  - Ruth Laxson, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - Lyle Ross, 1982-1995 (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth Lide and Paul Kayhart, 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - Ruth and David, 1983-1994 (Box 1)
  - Jeanette Stokes, 1986-1995 (Box 1)
  - Bob Trotman, 1989-1996 (Box 1)
  - John Ross, 1982-1996 (Box 1)
  - Marilyn Smith, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Melita Bryan, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Matilda and Alex Kirbysmith, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Andrew Forster, 1989-1992 (Box 1)
  - Pattie Belle Hastings, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
  - Gay Neale, 1986-1995 (Box 1)
  - Byrd Wade, 1989-1996 (Box 1)
  - Townsends (Box 1)
  - Stewart and Debbie Caudle, 1989-1992 (Box 1)
  - Deceased Pet Care Memorial Gardens and Crematory, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Grannie Pat, 1985-1989 (Box 1)
  - Congressman John Lewis (5th district of Georgia) (Box 1)
  - Fred Crouch, 1974-1995 (Box 1)
  - Gordon Lish, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Brad Brooks, 1996-1998 (Box 1)
  - Mark Gottsegen, 1983-1992 (Box 1)
  - Steve Snyder, 1987-1993 (Box 2)
  - Marilyn and Cheryl, 1995-1996 (Box 2)
  - Irene, 1983-1994 (Box 2)
  - Sarah Lentz, 1989-1995 (Box 2)
  - Ruth Laxson, 1986-1997 (Box 2)
  - Ruth Laxson, 1998-2005 (Box 2)
  - Ruth Laxson, 2006-2007 (Box 2)
  - Elizabeth Lide, 1976-2000 (Box 2)
  - Betty Hanes, 1983-1998 (Box 2)
  - E-mail with Malcolm Jones, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Letters and postcards to Mary Margaret, 1966-2001 (Box 2)
  - Letters and postcards, 1981-1998 (Box 2)
  - Letters and postcards, 1991-2007 (Box 2)
  - Letters and postcards, 1980-2007 (Box 2)
  - Cards from children, 2005 (Box 2)
  - Artwork, Caitlin and David Caudle, 1987-1989 (Box 2)
- Picture files
  - Photographs
    - Cuba, 2002 and 2004 (Box 2)
    - Ashe County, North Carolina (Box 2)
    - Mary Margaret in hospice (Box 2)
    - Now You Get It, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Mary Margaret and Malcolm Jones in Greensboro, North Carolina (Box 2)
    - Alaska trip, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Emma Ming Kayhart (Box 2)
    - Decatur, Georgia (Box 2)
    - Cumberland Island, Georgia (Box 2)
    - Mary Margaret with Della and Daphne (Box 2)
    - Nexus Press (Box 2)
    - Caudle Family, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Charles Byrd Wade, Jr. (Box 2)
    - Family (Box 2)
    - Nativity Scene (Box 2)
    - Mary Margaret (Box 2)
    - Installation piece, The Mattress Factory, Atlanta (Box 3)
      A friend's (name unknown) installation piece at the Mattress Factory in Atlanta. Dated in the late 1980s or early 1990s. Wade is in several of the photographs.
    - TULA Foundation Gallery, Atlanta, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Caitlin Caudle, 1998 (Box 3)
    - Now You Get It installation and opening shots, 1992 (Box 3)
    - Cuba and Key West, 2002 (Box 3)
    - Alaska, 1999, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Mary Margaret (Box 3)
    - Kilbuck relative (Box 3)
      Photographs of a Kilbuck relative visiting NC from Alaska. Books and research is available on the Kilbuck family who moved into Alaska in the early 1900s. They were well-known Moravian missionaries.
  - Slides
    - Mary Margaret and Malcolm Jones, Jr., 1983 (Box 3)
    - Now You Get It, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Photo albums
    - Weekend at Fred's (Box 3)
    - The Riverton-Home-of-the-Freeze-Your-Ass-Off-Lumbee-And-Best-Fried-Chicken-Ever-Lazy-Crazy-Maizie-Days-of-Summer-Reunion, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Costa Rica (Box 3)
  - Cuba, April 25th-May 3rd, 2004 (Box 3)
- Drawings, Writings, and Exhibits
  - Photocopy of artwork for Have You Ever Seen an Ugly Bride?, 1971 (Box 3)
    A book by Mary Margaret Wade and Elizabeth Lide.
  - Cartoons arranged alphabetically (Box 4)
    - A-R (Box 4)
    - S-Z (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous - to file (Box 5)
  - They Say captions (Box 5)
  - Ready to Go (Box 5)
  - Flip Side of Marilyn Quayle (Box 5)
  - Emperor's Clothes (Box 5)
  - They Say/Hamdige +/- (Box 5)
  - Cast of Characters (Box 5)
  - Eyebrow Migration (Box 5)
  - High Chaperone (Box 5)
  - Bad Thought (Box 5)
  - Caffeine Test (Box 5)
  - Wire to Which we are Down (Box 5)
  - Mood Milk (Box 5)
  - Printe Truth (Box 5)
  - School Trip to Orlando (Box 5)
  - AAR Studies in Religion (Box 5)
  - That Other Texan (Box 5)
  - Flannery O'Connor/Flip (Box 5)
  - Hambidge/New Yorker captions, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Triumvirate (Box 5)
  - Comparative Study (Box 5)
  - Love, Sex, and Death, 1994 (Box 5)
  - Estuary (Box 5)
  - Ten Thousand Points of Light (Box 5)
  - Routledge Sent to, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Old Drawings (Box 5)
  - Elvis Guitar (Box 5)
  - Strategy (Box 5)
  - Triumphant (Box 5)
  - Voice Mail (Box 5)
  - A Quick Read (Box 5)
  - Unbound (Box 5)
  - Three Pieces of White Bread (Box 5)
  - Refuses to Relinquish Jaws Motif (Box 5)
  - Leap (Box 5)
  - Harlequin (Box 5)
  - The Conversation (Box 5)
  - Snow Sled (Box 5)
  - Unnamed folders (Box 5)
  - Now You Get It, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Now You Get It pamphlets, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Bringing Home the Loot (Box 6)
  - A-Z, arranged alphabetically (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: an exhibition of the Letters of Ray Johnson, 1976 (Box 6)
    Printed materials from an exhibit at the North Carolina Museum of Art.
  - P.O.V. Cartoons (Box 6)
  - Odor Eaters (Box 6)
  - Ideas for Arts for Life (Box 6)
  - Notebooks, (3 notebooks, one titled Arts for Life) (Box 6)
  - Journal, 1987 Aug. 11-1993 Jan. 24 (Box 6)
  - Travel notebook, 1973 (Box 7)
  - Sketchbook (Box 7)
  - Arts festival of Atlanta, 1994 (Box 7)
    Printed booklet. Wade's transit bus card If you don't get art here, please get art somewhere was chosen by Arts Festival and was pulled at the last minute for fear of being sued by Charter Peachford Hospital, whose slogan was If you don't get help here please get help somewhere. (Note: Elizabeth Lide). Card printed on page 44; biographical information on page 72.
  - Exhibit booklets (Box 7)
  - Visual and in-progress (Box 7)
  - Ode to Mary Margaret Wade, 2007 (Box 7)
  - Program from the Mary Margaret Wade memorial service and I am a Mary Margaret Wade Fan fans, 2007 (Box 7)
  - Joy's Class's Magazine (Box 7)
    From The Atlanta School where Wade taught art. The Atlanta School is an independent school that incorporates art into all subject areas. (note: E. Lide)
  - Artist books by Mary Margaret Wade, (12 books) (Box 16)
  - Sprial notebook (Box 16)
  - Clippings (Box 16)
  - Correspondence (Box 16)
- Subject files
  - Georgia Abortion Rights League petition (Box 7)
    Signed by Norma McCorvey (Jane Roe of Roe vs. Wade).
  - Resource Center for Women and Ministry in the South file (Box 7)
  - Kilbuck family history, (3 bound typescripts)
    Mary Margaret Wade's great-grandparents were John and Edith Kilbuck, Moravian missionaries to Alaska.
    - The Joseph Henry Kilbuck family (Box 7)
    - Joseph H. Kilbuck: Excerpts from his letters (Box 7)
    - The Kilbuck Story (Box 7)
  - Resume and teaching philosophy (Box 7)
  - Travel Information
    - Alaska, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Cuba (Box 7)
    - Paris, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Hambidge (Box 8)
- Clippings
  - Biographies and obituaries (Box 8)
  - House of Magic (Box 8)
  - Cartooning + ists (Box 8)
  - Thousand Points (Box 8)
  - Nexus Press Olympiad (Box 8)
  - Other clippings, (9 folders) (Box 8)
  - Photocopied articles by Wendell Berry (Box 8)
- Ephemera
  - Mary Margaret Wade letterheads (Box 8)
  - Collection of religious odds and ends (Box 8)
  - Drafting supplies (Box 9)
    From Wade's ex-husband Malcolm Jones.
  - Campaign and political buttons (Box 9)
  - Bumper stickers (Box 9)
  - Diplomas
    - University of Georgia, 1970 (Box 9)
    - Howard University, 1973 (Box 9)
  - Paper book (Box 17)
  - Queens College 1967 Coronet (Box 17)
- Oversize items
  - Drawings, Writings, and Exhibits (Box 10)
    - Dearest Santa Clause manuscript (Box 10)
      RESTRICTED
  - Clippings (Box 11)
    - Newspapers clippings of Mary Margaret's cartoons (Box 11)
    - Book forum, October/November 2005 (Box 11)
  - Drawings, Writings, and Exhibits
    - Charcoal rubbing (Box 11)
    - Photocopies of drawings (Box 11)
  - Drawings, Writings, and Exhibits (Box 12)
    - Sketchbooks (Box 12)
    - Ten Thousand Points of Light (Box 12)
  - Drawings, Writings, and Exhibits (Box 13)
    - Children's artwork (Box 13)
    - Magazines (Box 13)
    - Pieces designed by Mary Margaret Wade (Box 13)
  - Posters (Box 14)
  - Newspapers (Box 14)
  - Ned Cartledge (Box 14)
  - Art Papers (Box 15)
  - Home: A Game and Activity Book for Children of All Ages (Box 15)
  - Posters (Box 15)
  - Poster (Opaperfolder OC:VII:9)
  - Art box (Opaperfolder OC:VII:9)
  - Art boxes (Opaperfolder OC:VII:9)